<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The child-birth or womans lecture. That is: A lecture vpon Chap. 1. ver. 57, 58. of the holie Gospell according to Luke very necessarie to bee read and knowne of all young married and teeming women, and not vnprofitable for men of all sortes. By. Chr. H.</title>
            <author>Hooke, Christopher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13702</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851767</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851767</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17058</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03581)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17058)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 711:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The child-birth or womans lecture. That is: A lecture vpon Chap. 1. ver. 57, 58. of the holie Gospell according to Luke very necessarie to bee read and knowne of all young married and teeming women, and not vnprofitable for men of all sortes. By. Chr. H.</title>
                  <author>Hooke, Christopher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Orwin, for Henry Hooke, and are to be sold in Paules Churchyard, by Raphe Iackson, at the signe of the Swanne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Chr. H. = Christopher Hooke.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (-A1, D4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17058:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17058:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Child-birth or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Lecture.</p>
            <p>That is: A Lecture vpon Chap. 1. ver. 57, 58. of the holie Gospell according to Luke; very neceſſarie to bee read and knowne of all young married and teeming Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and not vnprofitable for men of all ſortes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Chr. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 66.7.</bibl>
               <p>Before ſhee trauailed, ſhee brought foorth: and before her paine came ſhee was deliuered of a man Childe.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>emblem with symbols of two entwined snakes, two cornucopias, and two hands shaking</figDesc>
               <p>BY WISDOME PEACE BY PEACE PLENTY</p>
               <p>TO</p>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>Thomas Orwin,</hi> for <hi>Henry Hooke,</hi> and are to be ſold in Paules Churchyard, by <hi>Raphe Iackson,</hi> at the ſigne of the Swanne. 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17058:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17058:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull, and vertuous Gentlewoman, Mistres Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Sauel, grace, mercie, and peace, (from Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the fountaine of all heauenlie graces) be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Lecture right (Worſhipfull) whereof I preſume to make you the Patroneſſe, is compact of the notes obſerued in my reading, at the birthes of your two moſt ſweet iewels, Maſter <hi>Henry,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Edward Sauels,</hi> and now publiſhed, as for the common good of all that pleaſe to reade it; ſo to performe my promiſe made long ſince vnto you, and to bee a testimonie of the godlie care, which your Honorable Lady-mother, the Lady <hi>Paget</hi> &amp; your ſelfe had to ſhew all thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes vnto the Lord for his great mercie towards you. For no ſooner were you thorough the goodnes of God deliuered, but that both the one time and the other, I was ſent vnto from her Ladyſhip and your ſelfe, to giue thankes vnto the Lord on your behalfe: ſo that the ſunne had not ſhewed his beames before ſuch time as the ſame mornings, wherein you receaued thoſe bleſſings. We had the whole familie together, the right Worſhipfull your Father, and your Huſband, being alſo preſent; like as was her Ladiſhip her ſelfe, with your Worſhipfull ſiſter Mistres <hi>Baeſhe,</hi> performed this exerciſe, and ſang Pſalmes of thankeſgiuing. J wiſh as I nothing doubt, of your good continuance in this ſo holy a courſe, that all others, who are partakers of the ſame mercies, would alſo imitate &amp; follow your godly example and preſident herein: which they ſhould the rather do, if they could or would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider aright, how many ſingular bleſſings in this one thing doo concurre, for nothing hindreth ſo much our thankefulnes
<pb facs="tcp:17058:3"/>
vnto the Lod as the want of a right conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his great benefits, wherewith he ladeth vs, which either for lack of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight into them; or for that they ſeeme ordinarie, and befall vs euerie daie, and others aſwell as vs are therefore the leſſe of the greater ſorte regarded: but were we affected as wee ſhould, the more ordinarie that they are, the more thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full we ſhould be ſince our ſinnes euerie day deſerue to break the ordinarie courſe of them;<note place="margin">Dani. 4.24.</note> for that we breake not off our ſinnes by righteouſnes, nor our iniquities by mercie toward the poore. And ſince we ſee dailie, many to faile of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom we may iuſtifie in respect of our ſelues, for not to ſpeak of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Rahel</hi> and <hi>Ely</hi> his daughter in lawe; how many right godly and vertuous women, do daily in Childe-bed miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? They therefore who haue the good ſucceſſe which you now thriſe (the Lord be bleſſed for it) haue had, &amp; alwaies may haue; ought (with <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and you) acknowledge his great mercies to them. For though it were ordinarie to all in ſafetie to bee deliuered, which wee ſee is not: yet therein they ſhall finde many extraordinarie bleſſings, as by this lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they may partlie conceaue, but most plainelie may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand of themſelues, and by themſelues, if themſelues they will call to remembrance of their owne deliuerances, and not forget al their former distres (whereout, without the Lords hand, it had been impoſſible for them to haue been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered) through ioy of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> child, whom they haue brought into the world. Leauing therefore the further conſideration hereof vnto your Worſhip, and to all other godly and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Matrons, that haue taſted herein, how ſweet and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull the Lord is. I end, beſeeching you to accept of this my poore labour: and praying the Lord that it may be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto al, in ſtirring them vp to a greater thankefulnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord for his ſo great mercies beſtowed vpon them.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips to God, for you and yours in his praiers.</hi> Chr. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17058:3"/>
            <head>Luke: 1.57, 58.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>¶ Now Elizabeths time was fulfilled that ſhe ſhould be deliuered, and ſhe brought foorth a ſonne.</p>
               <p>And her neighbours and Coſins heard tell: howe the Lord had ſhewed his great mercy vpon her, and they reioyced with her.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho this <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was, whom here we haue mentioned, none I ſuppoſe to be ſo ignorant,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.6,</note> but that he knoweth. <hi>She was</hi> (ſaith this Euangeliſt) <hi>of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Aaron: her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was Zacharias a Prieſt, and both he and ſhe, iuſt before GOD, walking in all his comaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ordinances without reproofe.</hi> A notable pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne and example, not onely for miniſters, and their wiues, whoſe blameles conuerſation in all things, and at all times, ought to be a ſecond inſtruction vnto the people: but for all couples (as we tearme them) of what degree, or calling ſoeuer they bee, that they themſelues fearing the Lord, and walking in his wayes:<note place="margin">Iob. 1.5. Gen. 18.19.</note> they may not onely teach as did <hi>Iob,</hi> but commaund alſo as did <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> their ſonnes, and their houſhold, to knowe the way of the Lord, to doe righteouſnes and iudgement. For this the godly whome any care of religion hath touched, haue alwayes according to his commaundement done, and this of his mercie towards them he hath not left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewarded. <hi>Abraham</hi> his reward with God was excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:17058:4"/>
great, being made for this, as it were, one of his priuie councell. <hi>For ſhall I conceale or keepe any thing from Abraham</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>ſince he wil teach his ſonnes and his houſholde.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> who vſed euery day to ſanctifie his ſonnes, that is to prepare them vnto ſanctification, by teaching them how; though for his triall &amp; our example, in the chiefeſt of his proſperous felicitie he was humbled &amp; caſt down;<note place="margin">Iob. 42.12.</note> yet the Lord reſtored him againe and bleſſed his latter dayes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 101. Ioſu 24.15. Gen. 35.2. Act. 10.2.</note> more than his former. The like may be ſaid of <hi>Dauid,</hi> of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> of <hi>Iaacob,</hi> of <hi>Cornelius</hi> the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Captaine, and ſuch like; whoſe carefull obedience to the commaundements of the Lorde, with the no leſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t information of their houſholds therin, is ſet downe; &amp; their reward from the Lord by his ſingular bleſſings in great aboundance beſtowed vpon them, is as it were particularly noted. <hi>Zacharias</hi> therefore and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as no doubt they performed this duetie, ſo they are not alone, neither is the rewarde of their holy conuerſation the leaſt: for whereas <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was barren and long without a childe, wherby ſhe was a reproach among wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Lord for a reward maketh her fruitfull, and the mother, not of a meane babe, but of ſuch a one as a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before him of a woman was neuer borne. This bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that the Lord beſtowed vpon <hi>Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> his wife:<note place="margin">Matt. 12.11</note> the Euangeliſt S. <hi>Luke</hi> here ſheweth in theſe two verſes, and withall declareth how her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Coſins with her reioyced thereat. The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is heere amplified by three circumſtances: Firſt of the time, <hi>It was fulfilled:</hi> Secondly of the deliuerance, for at her full time ſhee was <hi>deliuered:</hi> Thirdly of the fruite it ſelfe: which was a <hi>ſonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To accompliſh, and fulfill the full, and the iuſt time, before the deliuerance, how exceeding great a bleſſing it is, may beſt be conſidered by the contrarie, which is when women bring foorth vntimely fruite, ſuch which as
<pb facs="tcp:17058:4"/>
the Prophet ſaith neuer ſeeth the ſunne.<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.8.</note> For this (beſides that it is a great griefe, to the mother, to haue her womb to be her childes Graue, and withall bringeth her to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teame darnger of her owne life, if not to death it ſelfe) is a curſe which the Lord threatneth to puniſh them with who doe rebelliouſly tranſgreſſe againſt him.<note place="margin">Hoſe. 9.11.</note> 
               <hi>Their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Hoſeah</hi>) that is their Children, which me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their glory <hi>ſhal flie away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the birth, from the wombe, and from the concedtion:</hi> that is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being conceiued, they ſhall not be quickned: or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quickned, they ſhall not in the wombe accompliſh the iuſt time the birth, wherby for glorie they receiue a kinde of diſhonour, and for comfort and ioy, ſorrow and griefe. Examples of this iudgement among the <hi>Iewes,</hi> no doubt but there were many though they are not recorded: for that as now, ſo then children in ſuch ſorte borne, were hid and not ſpoken of as appeareth by this, that <hi>Iob</hi> wiſhed vnto himſelfe.<note place="margin">Iob. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Why was I not hid as an vntimely fruite either as infants which haue not ſeene the light:</hi> which manner of ſecret, and cloſe hiding of them, ſheweth alſo how fearefull a curſe it is, when as thereby it is ſignified that both the mother is aſhamed of, and loatheth the fruit of her own bodie, &amp; that the eies of others are not able to endure the ſight thereof. Now though the wicked are not alwayes ouertaken with this curſe, but are made partakers of the contrarie bleſſing in ſuch great meaſure that not onely themſelues doe accompliſh the dayes of their deliuerance, but their beaſts alſo:<note place="margin">Iob. 21.10.11, &amp;c.</note> according to that which <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith: <hi>Their bullock gendreth and faileth not; their Cow calueth and caſteth not her calfe: they ſend foorth their children like ſheepe, ſignifying thereby the great number of their Children:</hi> Yet is this the ſpecial bleſſing, promiſed vnto the children of God, to them that ſerue him and hearken to his lawes, to heare and doe them, according as we read: <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. <hi>If thou hearken
<pb facs="tcp:17058:5"/>
to his voice and doe all that I ſpeake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 23, 26.</note> 
               <hi>there ſhall none caſt their fruit or be barren in the land, the number of thy dayes will I fulfill.</hi> This promiſe then we ſee the Lord maketh vnto his children, which he alſo performeth vnto them; as here vnto <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> vnles their ſinnes, as they hinder many other good things doe alſo hinder it.<note place="margin">Ier. 5.25.</note> And when he performeth it to them, it is a bleſſing from him, and a moſt ſure token of his fauour and louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes towards them: wheras to the wicked, though they commonly enioy the commoditie thereof, as they doe of the ſunne and the raine which ſhineth and falleth vpon the good and the bad,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.45.</note> the iuſt and vniuſt: Yet it is to them as are all other things of this life which they vſurp, but as a curſe heaping coales vpon their heads, and making their condemnation more grieuous.</p>
            <p>The next circumſtance whereby this bleſſing is am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, is, that ſhe was deliuered: which of it ſelfe howe great a mercy it is, may be conſidered alſo by the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which is, when either a woman who hath fulfilled her time, cannot be deliuered, or in ſuch ſorte after long and gieuous trauaile is deliuered, as therewith in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, and panges thereof ſhe endeth her life: <hi>This is</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hezechias) a day of tribulation: the Children are come to the birth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kin. 19.3.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; there is no ſtrength to bring forth:</hi> comparing the eſtate of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> beſieged by <hi>Zenache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib,</hi> and not able of it ſelfe to defend it ſelfe, to a woman trauailing of Childe at the full ende of her tearme, and yet wanting ſtrength to bring it foorth as though hee ſhould ſay, if a woman in ſuch a caſe is moſt miſerable, then moſt miſerable is our eſtate. This then ſufficiently declareth the lamentable condition of a woman in ſuch diſtreſſe. But conſider we it further by examples: what a day of tribulation was it to <hi>Rachel,</hi> when after many grieuous pangs and great difficultie, being deliuered, her ſorrowes decreaſed neither in hearing nor ſeeing that
<pb facs="tcp:17058:5"/>
ſhe had brought foorth a man childe into the worlde: but encreaſed, to the taking away of her life, in ſo much that yeelding vp the ghoſt; ſhee called her Child <hi>Ben-noni,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 35.18</note> 
               <hi>the ſonne of my ſorrow.</hi> In like manner what a day of tribulation was it to <hi>Phinehas</hi> wife, mentioned 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.19.<note place="margin">1. Sa. 4.19.</note> when not anſwering the women that ſtoode about her, who bad her not feare, for that ſhe had borne a ſonne: nor regarding at all the fruite of her wombe, ſhe named him <hi>Ica-bod,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The glorie of GOD is departed from Iſrael:</hi> and ſo with griefe of heart, repeating the words againe: <hi>The glorie is departed from Iſrael,</hi> ſhee departed alſo &amp; left her life; giuing the women ſtanding by to vnderſtand, that the glory of God being gone out of the land, which is, when his true religion and ſeruice is taken away, as it was then from them, the Arke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken by the Philiſtines: that there can no comfort be receiued, by Children, nor by life it ſelfe. A notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for the women to make them carefull of the true religion of God, who now together with their huſbands are ſo careleſſe thereof, that whether it depart from them or tarrie with them, they make no reckoning, for they account not the goſpell the glorie of England, as <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nehas</hi> wife accounted the Arke the glorie of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> to the therfore we muſt preach,<note place="margin">Eſay. 32.9.</note> as <hi>Eſay</hi> preached to the women of his time: <hi>Riſe vp ye women that are at eaſe, heare my voice ye careles daughters, hearken vnto my words:</hi> For aſſure your ſelues that what day the goſpell (which now ye neglect, and doe not regarde, reſpecting onely your pride, pleaſure, and profite) be taken from you, the fame day ſhall be taken from you the ornaments of your pride: as your high corked ſlippers, your golden Calls, &amp;c. yea your huſbands, who haue cheriſhed you, and your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; whome in great ſorrow ye haue brought foorth:<note place="margin">Eſay. 3.24.</note> and the Lord ſhall giue you for huſbands widowhead, for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren diſolutenes, for ſwéete ſauour ſtinck, for a girdle
<pb facs="tcp:17058:6"/>
a rent, for dreſſing of the haire baldnes, for a fine ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher ſack-cloth, and for beautie burning.</p>
            <p>Thus it befell to the women of <hi>Siloh:</hi> and thus the Lord threatneth to doe, as he did vnto them, and to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that are careles of his ſeruice, and rebellious againſt him. And therefore he ſendeth vs to <hi>Siloh,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Goe ye now to my place which was in Siloh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 7.12</note> 
               <hi>where I ſet my name at the beginning: and beholde what I did to it for the wickednes of my people Iſrael.</hi> But to returne from this digreſſion vnto <hi>Phinehas</hi> wife, ſhe is a patterne as I ſaid, in whome we may ſée the great diſtreſſe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of a woman lying in ſuch plight, that though at length ſhe be deliuered of her childe, yet ſhe is not deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from her paines, vntill ſhe be deliuered of her life: Yet this caſe in compariſon of theirs, who hauing accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed their full time and cannot be deliuered at all, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſomewhat tollerable. And of ſuch, hiſtories record ſome, and women no doubt, are priuie to many mo: from theſe perils and daungers, when the Lord deliuereth a woman, that not onely ſhe bringeth forth with the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of her life, but that before the trauaile ſhee bringeth foorth, and before her paine come ſhee bee deliuered of her Child: howe great mercie doth the Lord ſhew vnto that woman?<note place="margin">Eſay. 66.7.</note> This the Lord ſpeaketh of the ſodain reſtawra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church: <hi>Before ſhee trauailed ſhee brought foorth, and before her paines came ſhe was deliuered of a man Childe:</hi> declaring thereby that as he pleaſeth to giue ſuch a ſpeedy and eaſie deliuerance to ſome, whome it pleaſeth him, that as it were before their paines come they are deliuered; ſo he can and will when his Church is by al likelyhood in greateſt danger, euen as a woman is when ſhee boweth her ſelfe to trauaile of Child, vpon the ſodaine, deliuer it without paine and trouble, in the turning of an hand. This is more manifeſtly ſhewed in the <hi>Reuela,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 12.2.</note> 12. where the great danger of the Church
<pb facs="tcp:17058:6"/>
of God, and the miraculous deliuerance thereof, is ſet foorth vnder the ſimilitude of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trauailing in birth readie to be deliuered. Let women therefore, who are partakers of this mercy, as was <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> namely, to be both deliuered, and that without the dolefull continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in labour and trauaile many dayes, as many doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that the Lord beſtoweth vpon them an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie bleſſing to be wondred at; as it is in the former place of <hi>Eſay: Who hath heard ſuch a thing?<note place="margin">Eſay. 66.8.</note> Who hath ſeen ſuch things? aſſoone as Sion trauailed ſhe brought forth her children.</hi> For what is one woman in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the whole Church of God, men and women; and what greater mercie doth or can the Lord in this life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon them, than ſpéedelie (in ſuch diſtreſſe) when they call to heare and deliuer to them:</p>
            <p>The laſt circumſtance in this firſt verſe obſerued is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>ſhe brought forth a So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne:</hi> diuers we know bring forth monſters,<note place="margin">Luk. 16, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which can haue the name neither of ſonnes nor of daughters. In that therefore the Lord fréeeth <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> from this curſe, and graunteth her to bring foorth a childe, and he a man child, and ſuch a childe who ſhould be filled with the holy ghoſt, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mothers womb, to be the Prophet of the moſt high, and to goe before him in the ſpirit and power of <hi>Elias;</hi> it is the ſumme and the perfection of the former benefites: and that which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ordinarily, euen in ordinarie births, the ſorrowes in trauaile to be forgotten. This women know to be true by their own experience:<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.21.</note> And our Sauiour Chriſt (from whom nothing is hid) teacheth vs alſo the ſame, ſaying; <hi>A woman when ſhee trauaileth hath ſorrow becauſe her howre is come: but ſo ſoone as ſhe is deliuered of her Childe, ſhe remembreth no more the anguiſh: for ioy that a man is borne into the worlde.</hi> Where by <hi>Man</hi> hee meaneth aſwell the woman Childe as the man Childe, both being the great bleſſings of the Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:17058:7"/>
though in ſome reſpects: the man childe is preferred to the woman, as by whom the name, which men and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men moſt of all earthly bleſſings do deſire, is the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt in remembrance continued. And therfore the Godly men and women in the Scripture who haue béen barren haue eſpecially aſked of the Lord a ſonne:<note place="margin">Gen. 15.2.</note> ſo <hi>Abraham deſired a ſonne,</hi> that <hi>Eliezer</hi> the ſteward of his houſe might not be his heire.<note place="margin">1. Sa. 1.11.</note> And <hi>Anna</hi> prayed for a man child that ſhe might dedicate him to the ſeruice of the Lorde in his Temple: In which reſpect alſo it appeareth that the godly then deſired rather ſonnes than daughters; howſoeuer to ſerue the Lord in that office, ſeemeth now a thing ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temptible; though the miniſtrie of the goſpel be farre more glorious, as the Apoſtle notably ſheweth to the <hi>Corinth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.8.</note> than was the miniſtrie of the law: That euerie man (be he neuer ſo meane) diſdaineth; ſaue that neceſſity for want of other maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce conſtraineth him, to train vp his Sonne as <hi>Anna</hi> did her <hi>Samuel,</hi> to ſerue the Lord in that vocation: No maruaile therfore though the Lord diſdaine to giue them ſonnes, who doe diſdaine to conſecrate them vnto him; or if he giue ſuch ſonnes, no maruaile though as commonly we ſee his bleſſing be not vpon them, ſince of many they wil not ſpare him one, but if all other meane faile they will rather beſtow them vpon<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>at is to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, ciuill or <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mmon <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>wyers <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rchants, &amp;c. Hoſe. 9.14.</note> 
               <hi>Galen Iuſtinian</hi> &amp; <hi>Littleton,</hi> and commit them to the windes and the Seas, to aduenture thereupon their wittes, their goods, and their liues, and to other handiecraftes, than that they ſhould ſerue him to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in his Church. But to leaue complaining of ſuch to whom the Lord for this cauſe I doubt not giueth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times barren wombes and drye breaſtes. The iſſue whether it bee of Sonnes or daughters, it is a ſingular bleſſing, and the cheefe bleſſing of this life: for to bee bleſſed in the fruite of the wombe, excelleth the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the fruite of the ground;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 128.3.</note> the wife to bee as the
<pb facs="tcp:17058:7"/>
fruitefull Vine,<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.9. &amp; 13.</note> and the Children to bee as the Oliue branches round about the table, ſurmounteth the fatnes of the oliue, wherewith are honored, and the red bloud of the Grape, whereby are chéered both God and men; for ſonnes are more pleaſing than pleaſant plants, &amp; daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are more louely and glorious in parents eyes, than are the poliſhed corners of a temple. The Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in the 127. Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.4.</note> compareth Children to arrowes in the hand of a ſtrong man, and pronounceth him bleſſed, that hath his quiuer full of them: ſhewing alſo, wherein that bleſſednes dooth conſiſt, namelie in this,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
that they whome the Lord hath thus bleſſed ſhall not bée aſhamed when they ſpeake with their enemies in the gate:<note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.6.</note> for whereas their enemies would haue vpbraided them as accurſed, by reaſon of their barrennes, like as <hi>Peninnah</hi> did <hi>Anna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.1.</note> this their opprobrie by their hauing of Children, is taken away according to that with <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> here ſaieth of her ſelfe: and their mouthes as <hi>Anna</hi> ſaith, enlarged ouer their enemies. Thus then wee ſee what a bleſſing this was to <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that ſhee was made fruitefull, and brought foorth a ſonne, and how ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallie the fruite of the wombe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 127.3.</note> is an inheritance and bleſſing that commeth of the Lord. And this that it is ſo, is a moſt neceſſarie doctrine in theſe daies to be taught, in reſpect of two ſortes of people; the one who thinketh Children to be a charge: and therefore if they might haue their choiſe, had rather to bee without them than haue them.<note place="margin">Prou. 17.6,</note> How farre are ſuch from the knowledge of Gods trueth in this behalfe, which teacheth vs, that Children are a bleſſing, an inheritance, a reward, and a crowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs from the Lord: this if ſuch would duely conſider, it would both reforme their corrupt, and wicked iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this behalfe, and it would alſo comfort them in their diſtreſſe, being ouercharged in their owne eyes, with a charge of Children: for what greater comfort can
<pb facs="tcp:17058:8"/>
there bee, than with our eyes, ſenſibly to ſee the Lordes bleſſings and ſignes of his fauour before vs, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many in their Children cannot ſee, by reaſon of their ignorant hearts, which neuer were inſtructed in Gods ſchoole, they take more comfort in the increaſe of their ſwine, than they doo in the increaſe of ſonnes and of daughters. The other ſort, for whom the knowledge of this doctrine is neceſſarie, are they who taking delight, and that great as great may bee in their Children, they yet ſound not to the deapth of this bleſſing; they perceiue it not to be a bleſſing from the Lord, but doo take it to be a naturall and ordinarie worke of nature, whereby they both robbe the Lord of that honour, and thankes which is due vnto him, and depriue themſelues alſo of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ioye: which in the conſideration thereof the godlie doo coonceiue, who thereby perceaue the Lord, to haue a ſpeciall regarde vnto them, according as <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did, as it is manifeſt by theſe her owne words:<note place="margin">Luke. 1.25.</note> 
               <hi>Thus hath the Lord dealt with me in the daies that he looked vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me.</hi> Where we ſee that by her ſonne that ſhe had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, &amp; afterwards brought foorth: ſhe maketh an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto her ſelfe, that the Lord looked down vpon her; or as the Virgin <hi>Marie</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Luke. 1.48.</note> regarded her eſtate: than which aſſuredlie to knowe, as ſhe knew it perfectly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, what greater ioye could her heart conceiue? But leaſt by this generall ſpeach, it ſhoulde bee thought, that children are vnto all a token of God his fauour, and that from them they may reaſon as did <hi>Elizabeth: Thus hath the Lord dealt with me, in the daies that hee loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon me.</hi> It muſt bee vnderſtoode, as partlie in the beginning I ſignified, that theſe temporal things which the Lord beſtoweth indifferentlie, both vpon the good and the bad; are then vnto vs bleſſings and ſignes, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of the Lordes fauour and louing kindenes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs: when as wee, vppon whome they are beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
<pb facs="tcp:17058:8"/>
are ſuch, who doo from our hearts, loue, ſerue, and feare him? For otherwiſe, if he who receiueth them from the Lord is wicked and vngodlie, and doo continue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in without repentance, they are not vnto him bleſſings, but curſings, not pledges of his ſaluation thorough the grace and fauour of God in Chriſt: but heauie tokens, and certaine of his more grieuous condemnation. The Scripture therefore to put a difference, it thus ſpeaketh: <hi>Bleſſed is euerie one, that ſerueth the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 128.</note> 
               <hi>and walketh in his waies.</hi> And thereupon reckoning God his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vpon ſuch, in reſpect of the labors of their hands, in reſpect of the fruitefulnes of their Wiues, in reſpect of the towardlines of their Children: it thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth: <hi>Loe thus ſhall the man bee bleſſed, that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Lord.</hi> The feare therefore of the Lord, which is manifeſted, by a carefull watching in his waies: is it that ſanctifieth to vs the fruite of the womb, &amp; the fruite of the ground, which halloweth our baſket and our ſtore; and which bleſſeth our goings out, and our commings in: and maketh what euer we haue, be it ſmal or great, to be an exceeding bleſſing vnto vs. But with the wicked it is nothing ſo,<note place="margin">Iob. 21.7. &amp;c.</note> for though to vſe againe the words of holy <hi>Iob; They liue, waxe olde, and growe in wealth, though their ſeede be eſtabliſhed in their ſight with them, and their generation before their eyes: though their houſes be peaceable and without feare, and the rod of God be not vpon them: though their Bullock gendereth and falleth not, their cow calueth and caſteth not her calfe: though they ſend foorth their Children like ſheepe, and their ſonnes daunce: though they take the Tabret and Harpe, and reioyce in the ſounde of the Organes: though they want nothing that their heart wiſheth, or their eye luſteth after.</hi> In which caſe, thus laded with the things of this life, we (like as did <hi>Iob</hi>) doo often ſee the moſt vngodlie men, according to that the Pſalmiſt
<pb facs="tcp:17058:9"/>
ſaith. <hi>Loe theſe are the wicked, they proſper &amp; increaſe in riches, their eyes ſtand out for fatnes.</hi> Though I ſay all theſe things, and al other good things of this life befall them, according to their owne hearts deſire: yet neither Children nor any other thing elſe, though they haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered golde as duſt, and ſiluer as the ſtones of the ſtreat, is, or can be a crowne, or a bleſſing vnto them. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all thoſe things, <hi>the increaſe of their houſe</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 20.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall goe away, it ſhall flowe away, in the day of the Lords wrath, they ſhall periſh for euer, like their dung, and they that haue ſeene them, ſhall ſee them no more.</hi> Thus it is apparant, how that to the godlie one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, Children and all things are a bleſſing: as was this Sonne to <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which ſhee brought foorth, for that ſhe together with her huſband feared the Lord: walking in all his waies and ordinances without reproofe. So that to conclude this firſt part, we ſee, how in euerie cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, which the Euangeliſt here noteth, the Lorde his mercie towardes her appeareth:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uke. 1</note> as it dooth alſo to all them, to whome hee ſheweth the like fauour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, to fulfill their time, to bee deliuered, and to bring foorth their iſſue, whether it bee Sonne or Daughter.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the ſecond part, which ſheweth how her Neighbours,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uke. 1</note> and Couſins reioyced thereat. And herein theſe circumſtances are to bee obſerued, firſt, who they were that reioyced, ſecondlie how, and thirdly for what.</p>
            <p>They that reioyced were her Neighbours, and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins that is kinſfolke in generall. And here in parte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to bee fulfilled, that which the Angell foreſhewed to <hi>Zacharias</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">Luke. 1.14</note> to wit, that manie ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce at his birth. Which they did as in reſpect of <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> whoſe reproache hereby they ſawe to bee done away, whereof they could not, but bee right glad: ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciallie in regarde of that hope, which they had concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:17058:9"/>
of the Childe, by the relation of the Angell vnto <hi>Zacharias:</hi> both therefore for the benefit, as it reſpected <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and her Huſband particularlie, and for the bleſſing: which hereby the Church of GOD ſhoulde receiue generallie, did they thus at this birth reioyce. In the former they perfourmed the duetie of kinde Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and kindred; and in the latter the part of good and godlie Chriſtians. For to ſpeake of the former, it is the duetie of good Neighbours and kinſfolke to be glad, and to reioyce at the good of their Kindred, and Neighbours. So did (as the laſt yeare vppon like occaſion I ſhewed) the Neighbours of <hi>Naomie</hi> in the booke of <hi>Ruth:</hi> for when <hi>Ruth</hi> her Daughter in Lawe, was deliuered of a Childe by <hi>Obed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>The Women her Neighbours</hi> (ſaieth the text) <hi>ſaide vnto her in reioycing manner. Bleſſed be God which hath not left thee this day without a kinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: this ſhall bring thy life againe, and cherriſh thine old age, for thy daughter in law which loueth thee, hath borne vnto him, &amp;c.</hi> Thus alſo did <hi>Iob</hi> his bretheren, friends and acquaintance,<note place="margin">Iob. 42.11.</note> for they after the Lorde had turned the captiuitie of <hi>Iob,</hi> came vnto him, and brought preſents with them, to comfort him ouer the euill that the Lord had brought vpon him, and to reioyce with him for his recouerie there from.<note place="margin">Rom. 12.15.</note> This is to <hi>Reioyce with them that reioyce, and to weepe with them that weep:</hi> like as the Apoſtle commandeth: whereby it appeareth that ſuch good Neighbourhoode was then, and that it ought to be alſo now: for which cauſe, their example, and this commaundement is left vnto vs. But good neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhoode is now gone, the common complaint in euery place is: and Couſins kindnes is ſuch, that euen the name it ſelfe through Couſins that are Couſiners, is growne to bee odious, and a name of reproach: for ſo farre are men in theſe daies from reioycing at the good of each others, though they bee Neighbours the next doore
<pb facs="tcp:17058:10"/>
together, or kinſemen of the néereſt bloud, that they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repine and grudge, that any fat ſhould fall beſides their owne beards: and as for the weeping with them that are in affliction, thereby to comfort them, it may bée ſaide, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaide of his friends in the ſame reſpect: that in his behalfe men haue forſaken the feare of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie;<note place="margin">Iob. 6.14.</note> for whereas, <hi>Hee that is in miſerie ſhould bee comforted of his Neighbour,</hi> all his friends and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of the bretheren of the poore) do hate him, if not reuile him, as <hi>Iobs</hi> friends did him. This is a complainte more fitte for another place,<note place="margin">Prou. 19.7.</note> yet not amiſſe here, for that by the churliſhnes, and vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralnes of men in theſe daies, the loue of theſe Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours &amp; Kinſfolkes may the better appeare. For how e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer men in theſe daies, malice and grudge, they reioyced and were glad at the great bleſſing of the Lord beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon <hi>Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and would no doubt, if occaſion had béen, haue alſo comforted them, as manie of the Iewes did comfort <hi>Marie</hi> &amp; <hi>Martha</hi> for the death of their broher <hi>Lazarus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But as men faile in this dutie, ſo doe they no leſſe in that other, which is, <hi>to reioyce</hi> for the good which gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie befalleth the Church of God, for ſo careles are they of ſuch ſpirituall things, that for the moſt part, they ſee them not, or ſeeing them, they regard them not, for though an hundreth <hi>Ihon Baptiſts</hi> were borne, that is, though an hundreth, or a thouſand ſuch, who were able to preach vnto vs the Goſpell of Chriſt, for the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes, were ſent foorth by the Lord of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt to furniſh our own Churches, &amp; ſuch other as want their miniſterie: yet farre would many bee from reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing thereat, and from prayſing and bleſſing the Lord for ſo viſiting of his people, which alſo they would be, as they are in reſpect of ſundrie other good bleſſings, as for the bleſſing of good Magiſtrats, of peace, of plentie,
<pb facs="tcp:17058:10"/>
&amp;c. whereby the Church of God is made to flouriſh. For though theſe thinges done, they doe well like, and chiefelie deſire: yet it is onelie in reſpect of their owns priuate commoditie, and for the bodie ſake, for that they thereby alſo receaue benefite and pleaſure: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they would not reſpect them, in regard of the good that commeth thereby, eyther to their owne ſoules, or to the Church of GOD, for whoſe cauſe yet, and not for their owne, they doe inioye them.</p>
            <p>This their corruption appeareth manifeſtly hereby, for that though they heare of neuer ſo great diſtreſſe of the Church of God beyonde the Seas, they are thereby no more affected to weepe <hi>quam ſi dura ſilex, aut ſtet marpeſia mutis:</hi> than is the hardeſt flint, nor though they heare of neuer ſo good the ſucceſſe thereof, are they at all more affected to reioyce, than was <hi>Timon</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens:</hi> whereby they ſhew them ſelues not to be of the communion of Saints, nor members of the myſtical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt: betwixt whom is the like or greater <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathie,</hi> than is betwixt the members of this our naturall bodie, wherein if one member ſuffer, all ſuffer with it, and if one member be had in honor,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1 26.</note> all the other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers reioyce with it. This fellow feeling of the good of the church of God in general, by the birth of <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> had theſe neighbours and Couſins of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> for which cauſe at her deliuerance of him, they reioyced. And the like haue all they that are in deede of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, neyther can any truely ſay, that hee is a member of the bodie of Chriſt, vntill in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he be partaker of the ſame: And this may ſuffice for the parties that reioyced.</p>
            <p>The manner of their reioycing followeth to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, which though heere it be not expreſſed: yet in what ſorte, the Godlie haue vſed to reioyce, we cannot be ignorant, ſince elſe-where it is often and at large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.
<pb facs="tcp:17058:11"/>
               <hi>Simeon</hi> reioyced in ſinging,<note place="margin">Luke. 2.29</note> 
               <hi>Lord now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace. Marie</hi> in ſinging, <hi>My ſoule doth magnifie the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.46</note> This <hi>Zacharias</hi> in ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Luk. 1.64.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael that hath viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and redeemed his people.</hi> And the women that were at <hi>Ruths</hi> labour in ſaying,<note place="margin">Ruth. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed bee God, which hath not left thee this day without a kinſeman.</hi> By theſe and ſundrie others, as by that ſong of <hi>Anna,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2, 1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we may gather,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 2.1.2 &amp;c.</note> that the ſpirituall manner of reioycing either for this, or any other benefit, is, in yeelding thankes vnto the Lord, and praiſe vnto his name. For this the Lord requireth of vs, and this the Godlie hath bound themſelues, (as it were by ſolemne promiſe) to performe vnto him.<note place="margin">Pſa. 116.12 13</note> 
               <hi>What ſhal I render vnto the Lord</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid,) for all his benefites towards me?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 118.</note> 
               <hi>I will take the Cup of ſaluation and call vpon</hi> or praiſe <hi>the name of the Lord.</hi> And againe, <hi>Open ye vnto me the gates of righteouſneſſe, that I may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in and prayſe the Lord.</hi> And why? <hi>becauſe though he hath chaſtened me ſore,</hi> (as iuſtlie I haue deſerued) <hi>yet hath he not deliuered me to death</hi> (as in iuſtice hee might.) <hi>Lea,</hi> when ſhe had conceaued, &amp; borne her fourth ſonne, ſhe ſaide, <hi>Now will I praiſe the Lord:</hi> And that ſhe might the better bee put in minde of her promiſe in this behalfe, ſhe called his name <hi>Iudah,</hi> that is in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 29.35.</note> 
               <hi>praiſe.</hi> Thus to alleadge no moe examples, wee ſee how our manner of reioycing, as for other benefites, ſo namely for this great bleſſing of God, in giuing vnto vs an happie encreaſe of Children, conſiſteth in rendring praiſe and thankes vnto him. This if it goeth before, not in hipocriſie for a faſhion and ſhew, but in the ſinceritie of heart, and ſimplicitie of minde, then may other reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinges follow after,<note place="margin">Gen. 21.8</note> then may we wich <hi>Abraham</hi> make a feaſt, and vſe ſuch other ſemblances of ioye which the Godlie in the feare of God haue vſed, for by that, theſe
<pb facs="tcp:17058:11"/>
are ſanctified and made holie vnto vs, and without that, theſe are very prophane and heatheniſh, howe glittering a ſhew ſoeuer they make in the eyes of the world. Our firſt care therefore muſt be, if wee be true neighbours and kindred, to giue thankes vnto the Lord, to bleſſe his name, to yeelde praiſes vnto him for his benefites and bleſſings beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, or them, by whom we dwell, and with whom we are alied, for in ſuch ſorte no doubt, as all the Godlie haue vſed to doe, ſo the Godlie neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, &amp; Couſins of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> reioyced, and were glad; wherein they ſhewed themſelues rightly religious to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God; and hartie (not fained neighbours and friends) to their good neighbour and Couſin <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> But not onely they, as I ſhould haue noted in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part, reioyced, but ſhe alſo: for it is heere ſaide, <hi>that they reioyced with her. Elizabeth</hi> her ſelfe, as ſhee was the chiefe vpon whom this mercie was beſtowed, ſo was ſhe the chiefe, and as it were the ring leader, in giuing of thankes; for ſhe both ſtirred vp her ſelfe in thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to reioyce, and alſo vſed meanes to declare vnto her neighbours, &amp; her Couſins, what the Lord had done for her, that they alſo for it, with her might reioyce. For thus much doe theſe words declare, wherein it is ſaide, <hi>that her neighbours and Couſins heard tell, how the Lord had ſhewed his great mercie vpon her.</hi> For by whome ſhold they heare it, (eſpecially her huſband being dumb) but by her, or her meanes, who had receaued it, and therefore could beſt tell how to expreſſe it: For not onelie outwardlie as others, but inwardlie alſo did ſhe ſee, ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and feele, this great mercie of the Lord beſtowed vp<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> her. According therefore to that which in euerie reſpect, more than others ſhe knew, could ſhe, (as no doubt ſhee did) expreſſe each thing more fullie to the glorie of God.</p>
            <p>And this hath been the practiſe of the godly, alwaies in this behalfe to be blabs as we ſay, to blab foorth and
<pb facs="tcp:17058:12"/>
declare, what mercies the Lord hath powred foorth vpon them. <hi>Come vnto me,</hi> ſaith the Prophet: <hi>and I will tel you what the Lord hath done for my Soule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.16.</note> So <hi>Peter,</hi> when by the Angel of the Lord hee was deliuered out of priſon: he tolde the manner therof to them that were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together at <hi>Maries</hi> houſe,<note place="margin">Act. 12.17.</note> and willed them to ſhew the ſame things vnto <hi>Iames,</hi> and other the brethren: The like at our Sauiour Chriſt his commaundement, did the man out of whome the diuel was caſt: <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.27. He went and preached (ſaith the <hi>Euangeliſt</hi>) <hi>verſe,</hi> 39. tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout al the Citie what great things Ieſus had done vnto him.<note place="margin">Luke. 8.27.</note> For this, euen as by this one exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, the Lord requireth of vs, that wee ſhould doe both concerning priuate and publique benefites: to rehearſe and to ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foorth vnto others; leaſt the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of them ſhould die, and be forgotten: and ſo the Lord loſe his honour due vnto him for them. This was moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerued by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo long as among them remained any, eyther care or conſcience of the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God,<note place="margin">Pſal 78 2.3. &amp;c.</note> as is manifeſt by the 78. Pſalme: wherein is ſhewed both how the Lord commaunded, and they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed vnto him this duetie, by ſhewing foorth his prayſes, his power, and wonderfull workes vnto their Children, according as he eſtabliſhed it for a teſtimonie in <hi>Iaacob,</hi> and ordained it for a law in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But when they began to be careles of his ſeruice, and to wax wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his religion; then decayed likewiſe in them, this duetie of remembring each other of the benefites of God towards them: inſomuch that it is ſaid in the 2. of <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 2.10.</note> that <hi>Ioſuah</hi> being dead and that generation: there followed a generation, which neyther knew the Lord nor the workes which he had done for <hi>Iſrael:</hi> yea euen that miraculous worke of bringing them foorth of <hi>Aegipt</hi> was quite buried in obliuion, as if it had neuer been. And thus it is to be doubted, it will fare or ere it be long with
<pb facs="tcp:17058:12"/>
vs: for whereas the Lord hath beſtowed vpon euerie one of vs particularly, and vpon this land generally, as great bleſſings, in reſpect both of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things of this life, &amp; of the things concerning the life to come; as euer he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon that people of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> yet ſo careles is both preacher and people, one and other, that I feare mee ſhortly all will be forgotten, and not ſo much as that our miraculous deliuerance from the <hi>Spaniſh inuaſion</hi> bee kept in remembrance: we can talk and prate faſt enough of vanitie, and of the idle conceites of our own heart and braine: Yea we can readely blabbe, and tell foorth what may iniurie one another in his goods or good name, for to one of theſe endes tendeth moſt of our communication in theſe dayos, ſaue that much of it alſo is wanton and vnbeſeeming Chriſtians, ſuch as corrupteth good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and grieueth the holy ſpirite of God by whom we are ſealed vnto the day of redemption.<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.39.</note> But to tell forth what the Lord hath done for our ſoules, as did <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.16.</note> what great things Ieſus hath done for vs, as did the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed; what great mercies he hath ſhewed vpon vs,<note place="margin">Luke. 8.39.</note> as <hi>Elizabeth</hi> here did: or what deliuerances, benefites, and bleſſings he hath, and ſtill dayly doth beſtowe vpon vs, and our land, that thereby we might the rather ſtirre vp our ſelues and others to praiſe the Lord, to pray for the continuance of his louing kindnes towardes vs: in theſe caſes, and ſuch like, wee are mute as a fiſh, or as the dumb, that openeth not his mouth. This corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on howſoeuer it hath ouertaken vs: yet now let vs bee ſcholed by this vertuous woman, and learne of her for our amendment in this behalfe theſe two leſſons: namely our ſelues vpon whome God hath powred foorth his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; firſt to reioyce in thankfulnes and praiſe to his name: and then to communicate and declare it to others, that they with vs, and wee with them may doe the ſame. For thus wee ſee <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did, her ſelfe ſhe reioyced,
<pb facs="tcp:17058:13"/>
and certified her neighbours and Coſins how great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie the Lord had ſhewed vpon ner: for which cauſe they alſo (when they heard tell thereof) reioyced with her.</p>
            <p>What this great mercy was which the Lord had ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> may be vnderſtood by that which hath been ſaid: to wit, that whereas ſhe had been a long time barren, and thereby a reproach among women; now the Lord had giuen her to conceaue, to accompliſh her full time, to be deliuered, and to bring foorth a Sonne. Euery one of theſe is a great mercie, as ſeuerally it hath been ſhewed, how much more then, when they come all together in their ful perfection, as a reeke of Corne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in due ſeaſon into the Barne. This teacheth wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men eſpecially, and ſo al other generally, what account they haue to make of the conception and bearing of their Children, and from whence it doth proceede: namely that they haue to account of it as of a great mercy, and as proceeding from the great mercy of God. Wretched therefore are they that account it as an ordinarie thing, proceeding onely from the mutuall coniunction of man and woman: for who hath ſo bewitched them, that they ſée not many to want this bleſſing? to die without an heir, and to leaue their poſſeſſion to ſtrangers, if not to enemies; though a long time begininng in the flower of their age: they haue liued a married life?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 30.1.2</note>This opinion it ſeemeth <hi>Rahel</hi> had conceiued, when ſhe ſaid to <hi>Iaacob,</hi> giue me Children or elſe I die; but <hi>Iaacob</hi> corrected her fondnes ſaying: am I in Gods ſteed that I ſhould giue thee Children. Children therefore againe wee ſee come of God; without whoſe bleſſing a woman remaineth barren, not able to conceiue: or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, without ſtrength to bring foorth her fruite. Looke therefore, and account howe many Children you haue borne, and reckon that ſo many mercies, yea great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
<pb facs="tcp:17058:13"/>
(whereof euerie one containeth a number of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies) ye haue receaued from the Lorde.</p>
            <p>That wheras others haue remained as dry Chippes, you haue beene as fruitfull Olyues in your huſbands houſes. And this, as you muſt account a mercie, ſo you muſt acknowledge it to proceede from the free mercie of God; without any deſert or merit of yours, it is from his mercie that you conceaue, that you fulfill your time, that you are deliuered of Children, not of Monſters. Were it not for his mercie, your ſinnes (euen the beſt of the whole Sexe) deſerue, that in ſome of theſe, if not in al of theſe you ſhould miſcarrie.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.16.</note> The multipliyng of your paines in the conception &amp; bringing foorth, it proceeded of the curſſe of God, the deliuerance from thoſe paines, that therein you periſh not, it is of the great mercie of God. This <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and her Couſins here confeſſe, &amp; and this no doubt, all ſuch women as feare God, do with thankeſgiuing acknowledge.</p>
            <p>And this cannot be, but a great comfort vnto you, to conſider when as in other thinges, ſo in your children eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie, you haue ſuch notable pledges of the Lord his mercie towards you; for thus may you ſay, if the Lord in this and this child, and ſo in all the reſt had not ſhewed me contrarie to my deſerts great mercie, the curſe of ſorowes (which iuſtlie I deſerue) had ouerwhelmed me, that I ſhould neuer haue liued to haue praiſed the Lord in the Land of the liuing. As therefore (to conclude) you haue the greateſt tokens of God his mercie towards you, ſo you muſt labour, that in you may appeare the greateſt ſignes of all dutifull obedience vnto the Lord: otherwiſe the Lord for your vnthankefulneſſe will cut off his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies from you, whereby you ſhall die, not onely in your ſorrowes, to the loſſe of your liues, but in your ſinnes, to the loſſe of your ſoules. But if according to the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all holy Matrons, and eſpecially of this our <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17058:14"/>
you render thankes vnfaynedlie, &amp; cauſe thanks by many to be rendred vnto the Lord for his great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies vpon you, then be you aſſured, that his mercies ſhal neuer ceaſe from following you in this life, till you haue receaued the ſumme of all mercies in life euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>Thus we haue heard what bleſſings the Lord beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and how ſhe, her neighbours and Coſins reioyced thereat, in rendring praiſe and thankes for the ſame vnto the Lord. Now let vs pray vnto our good God, and louing father in Ieſus Chriſt, yeelding vnto him all praiſes and thankes for his great mercie alreadie ſhewed, as generally vpon vs all, ſo particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for his great mercies towards her, for whoſe cauſe eſpecially we are aſſembled, to reioyce in thankefulnes vnto him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata</head>
            <p>
               <hi>In the</hi> 4 <hi>Pag. lin.</hi> 1. <hi>for</hi> Lod <hi>read</hi> Lord. <hi>Pag.</hi> 11. <hi>lin.</hi> 15. <hi>for</hi> deliuer to <hi>read</hi> to deliuer. <hi>Pag.</hi> 15. <hi>lin.</hi> 9. <hi>for</hi> ſerueth, <hi>read</hi> feareth, <hi>&amp; li.</hi> 16. <hi>for</hi> watching, walking. <hi>&amp; lin.</hi> 28 <hi>for</hi> falleth, faileth. <hi>Pag.</hi> 18. <hi>li.</hi> 6 <hi>for</hi> his, this. Pag. 19. <hi>lin.</hi> 14. <hi>for</hi> mutis, cautes. <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. <hi>lin.</hi> 9. <hi>for</hi> ſpirituall, ſpeciall.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:17058:14"/>
            <head>The thankeſ-giuing.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord our God moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and moſt mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Ieſus Chriſt, wee thine humble ſeruants doo yeelde vnto thy diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie through him, (in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onlie thou art well pleaſed;) all poſsible thanks from the bottome of our heartes, for all thy benefits and bleſsings, both publique and priuate of bodie and of ſoule, which from thy bountiful hands in great mercie we haue receiued. And eſpeciallie O Lord we praiſe and magnifie thy glorious name, for thy great mercies beſtowed vpon thine handmaide, in giuing her to conceiue, to accompliſh her ful time, and to bring foorth a man-childe into the world. This mercie thou haſt reuealed vnto vs out of thine holie word, to bee a great mercie, and from thy great mercie onelie to proceede: ſo O Lorde we doo acknowledge it, ſo wee accept it; confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing no power to bee in any creature in Heauen or in earth to bring the ſame to paſſe, nor worthines, or merit to binde thee thereunto. For this thy great mercie therefore towards her; wee extoll and laude thy name, reioycing with her in all thankfulnes and reuerence (on her behalfe,) vnto thy maieſtie: and we further in Ieſus Chriſt his name, moſt humblie beſeech thy fatherlie good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:17058:15"/>
as thou haſt thus mercifullie begun ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue on thy louing fauour and kindenes towards her, and the ſweete infant which ſhe hath brought foorth into the world. O Lord ſtrengthen her by thy power, comfort her by thy ſpirit, that howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer now ſhe be brought into a lowe and a weake eſtate, that yet in due time, ſhee may recouer her former ſtrength, and be able to come to giue thee praiſe for her gracious deliuerance, and for all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy bleſsings, with the reſt of thy Saints in the great congregation. Bleſſe alſo O Lord her infant, that as ſhee hath ſuſtained ſorrowe and paine in bearing it in her womb, and in bringing it foorth, ſo by thy bleſsings vpon it, ſhe may receaue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ioyce; when not onelie ſhee may ſee it to haue receaued the Sacrament of new birth, but when comming to age of diſcretion, it ſhall mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, by a godlie and an holy life: that it is borne a new and regenerate in ſpirite, and is of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, with whom thou haſt made this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious couenant, I will be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed. For theſe graces, O Lord our God as we pray thus particularly, (in regard of this preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) ſo we beſeech thee to enlarge thy ſelfe in al other neceſsarie mercies to vs, and to thy whole Church generallie, eſpeciallie in the pardoning, &amp; forgiuing of our ſinnes, according to thy promiſe in Ieſus Chriſt, in whoſe name (with the ſame words which he hath taught vs,) we pray further vnto thee, ſaying, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17058:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
